Finding Aid for Right to Decency Organizational Records, 1985-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Right to Decency Organizational Records 1985-2006
Right to Decency (Organization)
0610 Bj 2
The Right to Decency organization was centered in Macomb County, Michigan, and was dedicated to the elimination of “the vast amount of pornography and obscenity inundating society.” The record group includes correspondence, organizational records, meeting minutes, newsletters, flyers, articles, and recordings regarding the activities and administration of the organization.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received on November 29, 2005 from the organization's founders, MaryEllen and Art Gavin (donor no. 9673 ).
The record group is open to research.
MaryEllen and Art Gavin founded Right to Decency, Inc., in 1986 at St. Malachy Parish, Sterling Heights, Michigan. The organization began when pornographic magazines, which were in full-view at the local drugstore, dismayed MaryEllen Gavin. Ellen began a dialogue between the vice-president of the drugstores' headquarters and her parish and surrounding area churches. She and her allies insisted that the store cover the magazines and get them out of view. Success ensued, when the entire chain of 80 stores, made a corporate decision to stop the sale of pornographic magazines entirely. With that success, 12 persons began to meet each month, educating themselves about the ways they could work against pornography and obscenity. They discovered existing laws, which prohibited the distribution of these materials. They began to contact the public, eventually mailing their newsletter on a quarterly basis to more than 330 Catholic churches in the archdiocese, to 50 Protestant churches and about 700 families, informing them of what could be done to curtail activities of the pornography industry.
Right to Decency was sponsored by St. Malachy parish until incorporated in 1993. The organization operated as a Resource Center, staying informed about local and national issues which related to maintaining a healthy, moral, community environment. The group educated the public by explaining their own 'success stories' in working against indecency as well as providing the expertise of other state and national decency organizations. One early resource used, was the book Final Report of the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography, published in 1986 (Introduction by Michael J. McManus). Also see the list of books and other materials, etc. distributed free of charge to the public when Right to Decency disbanded. This list is found in the "Bentley Historical Library" folder within the Correspondence series.
The group relied on Federal Communications Commission (F.C.C.) regulations when monitoring offensive dialogue and programming on radio and television. They also worked with federal, state and local government to improve existing laws and used these laws to protest illegal pornography and obscenity in movies, magazines, the Internet, at the public library and at local businesses.
Protests consisted of letter-writing campaigns, seen in the Correspondence Series containing letters to local and national politicians, to government agencies and to the local newspapers and radio programs. They also used other tactics such as boycotting, petitioning, picketing and publicity to create change.
The group was not solely about anti-obscenity issues. They advocated issues regarding traditional family values such as sexual abstinence before marriage, traditional marriage between one man and one woman, pro-life from birth until a natural death and the power of prayer. They also promoted national decency campaigns in the Southeast Michigan area such as the White Ribbon Against Pornography (W.R.A.P.), National Day of Prayer, and Turn Off TV Day campaigns.
MaryEllen and Art Gavin decided to retire after 21 years. They could not find a person(s) to lead the non-profit, volunteer organization or to manage the Right to Decency extensive website. They contacted the Detroit Archdiocese of Detroit and asked if they would take over the Right to Decency Website. The Archdiocese declined, explaining that their budget was downsized in recent years. They said they had no one to maintain the website and no one knowledgeable to answer questions from the public even if they had the funds. Interested churches and persons received much of the Right To Decency materials at no charge.
The American Decency Association in Fremont, Michigan, Morality in Media in New York, New York and the Thomas More Law Center in Ann Arbor, Michigan were the recipients of Right To Decency's remaining revenue.
The Southeast Michigan organization, Citizens for Responsible Broadcasting, (See www.responsiblebroadcasting.com/) received the "pending" Right to Decency radio complaints, which are still being investigated by the Federal Communications Commission (F.C.C.) in Washington, D.C. (M.E. Gavin, April 20, 2006)
The Right to Decency records include correspondence, organizational records, meeting minutes, newsletters, flyers, articles, and recordings regarding the activities and administration of the organization.
Subjects:
Right to Decency (Organization); Pornography--Michigan.; Pornography--Law and legislation.; Pornography--Moral and religious aspects.; Macomb County (Mich.); Obscenity (Law)--Michigan--Macomb County.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Right to Decency (Organization); Warren (Mich.). City Council.; Pornography--Law and legislation.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Background and Administration 1986-2006
  The Background and Administration series, 1986-2006, (0.50 linear feet) contains documents regarding the organization's founders, the goals and objectives, meeting minutes, publications, and acknowledgments.
  - Background
    - About RTD 2000-2005 (Box 1)
    - Acknowledgments and Certificates 1994-2002 (Box 1)
    - Founders, MaryEllen and Art Gavin 1999-2003 (Box 1)
    - Founder, Art Gavin, Anti-Pornography Conference Notes 1989 (Box 1)
    - Goals and Objectives 1987-2004 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings about RTD 1991-2000 (Box 1)
    - Photos, various RTD activities 1993-2005 (Box 1)
  - Administration
    - Financial Records 1989-2005 (Box 1)
    - Grant Letters and Applications 1993-2002 (Box 1)
    - Job Descriptions 2000-2004 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes 1985-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, Board and Corporate Meetings 1987-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Member, Charles Giacona 1994-2001 (Box 1)
    - Publications and Newsletters 1993-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Speaking Engagements and Notes 1990-2003 (Box 1)
    - Website content 2001-2006 (Box 1)
- Activities and Projects 1985-2005
  The Activities and Projects series, 1985-2005 (0.75 linear feet) contains records pertaining to the organization's activities advocating decency and prayer, and involvement in local and national events. The most prominent event RTD was involved in was the White Ribbon Against Pornography campaign sponsored by Morality in the Media of New York. RTD publicized this annual event by distributing ribbons and printed material to all Catholic churches in the Archdiocese of Detroit (330 churches), plus about 50 Protestant churches, other organizations and many hundreds of individuals. RTD also annually mailed packets of White Ribbon campaign instructions to all churches and to persons who requested the information.
  - Billboard Project 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Boycotting Instructions 1987-2003 (Box 1)
  - National Day of Prayer 1995-2001 (Box 1)
  - Picket Information 1985-1993 (Box 1)
  - Thanksgiving Parade, Warren, MI 1998-2004 (Box 1)
  - Turn Off TV Day 1998 (Box 1)
  - White Ribbon Against Pornography (WRAP) Campaign
    - General Information 1994-2004 (Box 1)
    - WRAP Campaign Publicity 1993-2004 (Box 1)
    - WRAP Campaign 1988-1993, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - WRAP Campaign 1994-2004, 8 folders (Box 2)
- Affiliated Groups 1985-2006
  The Affiliated Groups series, 1985-2006, (.25 linear feet) contains records of the relationship between RTD and Catholic parishes and Protestant churches who were working for decency (against illegal pornography and obscenity). RTD had monthly meetings at, and was funded by, St. Malachy parish, initially reaching out to more than 200 churches. Later in 1993, when RTD received a Grant from the archdiocese of Detroit Catholic church, (Peace and Justice Commission), they increased their mailing list to include all the Catholic churches in the Detroit Archdiocese as well as 50 Protestant churches and 700 other subscribers. In 1993, RTD registered in Lansing as a corporation and moved to 'donated' office space in Roseville, MI.
  - Citizens for Decency Through Law and Letters, Inc. 1987-2004 (Box 2)
  - Concerned Men Against Rape 1997-2000 (Box 2)
  - Dove Foundation 2000-2005 (Box 2)
  - Knights of Columbus 1996-2004 (Box 2)
  - St. Malachy Church
    - Bulletins 1985-1987, 1990-1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "The Winnable War" film 1988 (Box 2)
  - Vicariates 1990-2006 (Box 2)
- Political Figures, Agencies, and Legislation 1990-2004
  The Political Figures, Agencies, and Legislation series, 1990-2004, (0.50 linear feet) includes information about RTD's interest and involvement in the local and national, political arena. Most of these records include correspondence and notes about specific legislation, government agencies, and prominent political figures.
  - Agencies
    - FCC Complaints 1993-2004 (Box 2)
    - Macomb County Board of Commissioners 1990-2002 (Box 2)
    - Macomb County Prosecutor's Office 1990-1999 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Attorney General 1999-2004 (Box 2)
    - Michigan State Liquor Control Commission 2000-2003 (Box 2)
    - U.S. Administration 1992-2004 (Box 2)
  - Figures
    - Carl Marlinga 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Alan Sears, Attorney General's Commission of Pornography 1993 (Box 2)
    - Janet Reno 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Teresa Tomeo 2000-2004 (Box 2)
  - Legislation
    - Correspondence, Legislators 1992-2004 (Box 2)
    - Regulating Porn on the Internet, Bill No. 936 2000 (Box 2)
    - Regulating Adult Businesses, Bill No. 1524-34 2000 (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1985-2006
  The Correspondence series, 1985-2006, (1.0 linear feet) contains all of Right to Decency's correspondence. Letters and emails are in chronological order, and they record the organization's communication with individuals and organizations.
  - Bentley Historical Library 2006 (Box 3)
    (with computer disk)
  - Cardinal Adam J. Maida 1995-2005 (Box 3)
  - John LaLonde 2001 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Editors 1994-2003 (Box 3)
  - Tim Voss 2001-2005 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence Letters 1985-2006, 24 folders (Box 3)
- Campaign for Decency 1985-2005
  The Campaign for Decency series, 1985-2005, (1.0 linear feet) includes the organization's protests against various media outlets such as movies, television and radio. The organization also campaigned against sexually oriented businesses in the Southeast Michigan area. RTD was opposed to the vast proliferation of pornography, especially when in view of children (Violation of "Harmful to Minors Act" P.A. No.33 of 1978, revised since then) and distribution of obscenity (violation of P.A. No. 343 of 1984). Right to Decency was actively involved with legislators in revisions to the Michigan obscenity law (P.A. No. 343 of 1984) in 1991-2002 testifying in Lansing and at other locations. They were diligent in keeping notes, reports and clippings about these issues.
  - Businesses
    - Arbor Drugstore, Ann Arbor, MI 1985-1989 (Box 4)
    - Bookworld, Warren, MI 1996-1999 (Box 4)
    - Johnny B Good Bar, Warren, MI 1995-2001 (Box 4)
    - Jon Jon's, Warren, MI 1999-2001 (Box 4)
    - Kmart 1985-1995 (Box 4)
    - Lingerie Shows 2000-2001 (Box 4)
    - Massage Parlors 2000 (Box 4)
    - McDonald's, Wayne's World Promotion 1993 (Box 4)
    - Meijer 1995-2002 (Box 4)
    - Noir Leather, Royal Oak, MI 1997 (Box 4)
    - Roger's Roost, Sterling Heights, MI 2001-2004 (Box 4)
    - Scholastic Book Club 2000-2004 (Box 4)
    - Snooker's Pool & Pub 2001 (Box 4)
  - General Concerns
    - Chastity in Michigan 1986-2005 (Box 4)
    - Internet Porn, Filtering 1996-2005 (Box 4)
    - Library Internet Access 1996-2000 (Box 4)
    - Library Internet Access, ALA 1998-2002 (Box 4)
    - Magazines 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Movies
      - NC-17 Rating 1987-1995 (Box 4)
      - "Last Temptation of Christ," 1988 (Box 4)
    - Prostitution in Michigan 1998-2002 (Box 4)
    - Radio
      - Boycotting Advertisers 2004 (Box 4)
      - WKRK, "Kramer and Twitch Show," 2001-2003 (Box 4)
      - WKRK, "Tom Leykis Show," 2000-2001 (Box 4)
      - WKRK, "Deminski and Doyle Show," 2002-2004, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Rape in Michigan 1992-2001 (Box 4)
    - Sex Education 1991-1996 (Box 4)
    - Sexually Oriented Businesses (SOB)
      - Adult Bookstores 1991-2002 (Box 4)
      - General Information 1990-2005 (Box 4)
    - Television
      - Complaints to Advertisers 1999-2005 (Box 4)
      - CLeaR TV (Christian Leaders for Responsible TV) 1986-1989 (Box 4)
      - NYPD Blue 1992-1994 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan 1991-2001 (Box 4)
- Telephone logbooks 1990-2006
  The Telephone notebook series dates from 1990 to 2006, and provides notes on Right to Decency telephone conversations. The notes summarize work completed on that day.
  - 1990-2006 (Box 5)
    (include notes on conversations and organizational activities)
- Audio and Visual Tapes 1997-2002
  The Audio and Visual series, 1997-2002, (.50 linear feet) includes VHS and cassette tapes. The tapes contain recorded meetings of the Warren City Council where RTD members spoke about sex businesses, the White Ribbon Campaign, and other community issues. Other tapes contain cable TV shows featuring the RTD Co-Founder and other RTD members, and various cassettes contain radio interviews about topics such as NYPD Blue TV and other topics about the media.
  - Sound cassettes, 6 tapes
    - NYPD Blue August 30, 1993 Art Gavin and Gary Alwardt (Box 5)
    - WKRK FM 97.1 January 9, 2002 Deminski and Doyle Show (Box 5)
    - WMUZ FM 104.5 July 1, 1999 Shelley Asbury, Host Mark Gilman (Box 5)
    - WMUZ FM 103.5 January 10, 2001 MaryEllen Gavin, Host Teresa Tomeo (Box 5)
    - WMUZ FM 103.5 October 2, 2001 MaryEllen Gavin, Host Teresa Tomeo (Box 5)
    - WMUZ FM 103.5 October 19, 2001 MaryEllen Gavin, Host Teresa Tomeo (Box 5)
    - WMUZ FM 103.5 October 2002 MaryEllen Gavin and Dick Rolfe, Host Teresa Tomeo (Box 5)
  - Videotapes, 20 videotapes VHS (TM)
    - Catholic Council of Women, MaryEllen Gavin February 1, 1996 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Item #11C May 27, 1997 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Library vs. Pornography June 10, 1997 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Library vs. Pornography July 22, 1997 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Gloria Sankeur October 15, 1997 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, On Anti-nudity Ordinance December 14, 1997 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Gloria Sankeur and Shelly Asbury February 2, 1999, March 9, 1999 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Shelly Asbury speaks about "Glory Holes" May 25, 1999 (Box 5)
    - City Council Meeting, Chuck Busse-President November 9, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Gloria Sankeur Walby Interview November 1997 (Box 5)
    - Lumin Christi Interview, MaryEllen Gavin 2001 (Box 5)
    - Lumin Christi Interview, MaryEllen Gavin 2002 (Box 5)
    - Morality in the Media Teleconference, "A Plague on Society" May 9, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Right to Decency, MaryEllen Gavin, Connie Spisak, and Raquel Bowles, "Growing Older, Feeling Young" May 23, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Sports Illustrated, Boycotting Advertisers 2005 (Box 5)
    - Warren City Council Meeting June 24, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Warren City Council Meeting July 27, 1999, October 26, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Warren City Council Meeting, Reports on Studies About Secondary Negative Effects October 26, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Warren City Council Meeting October 26, 1999, November 9, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Warren New Conference April 4, 2000 City Council Meeting, April 11, 2000 City Council, SOB Hearing, May 9, 2000 (Box 5)